Over summer vacation,
I got my motorcycle license,
夏休み中に自動二輪の免許を取って
and my number plate changed
from white to yellow.
ナンバープレートは白から黄色に変わった
私のカブはシノさんの店でエンジンブロック修正をしてもらい
I had the engine block on my Cub
modified at Shino-san's shop,
原付から原付二種になっていた
turning it from a motorbike
into a type II motorbike.
49cc から 52cc へ　5％ の排気量アップ
It went from 49 cc to 52 cc,
for a 5% increase in displacement.
これで道路を問わず　30 キロ制限だった最高速度が
Now, my speed limit, which had been
30 kph no matter what street I was on,
他の自動車と同じになった
was now the same as
all the other vehicles.
正直　スピード以外
Honestly, aside from the speed,
I can't tell much difference from
everything else up to now.
今までとの違いはあまりわからない
けど　なんだか少し　自由になれたような気がした
Still, for some reason,
I felt a little bit more liberated.
やっぱり　カブはおもしろい
My Cub really is fascinating.
"Super Cub Episode 6"
"My Cub"
My Cub really is fascinating.
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
"2nd Year"
え～いよいよ明日は　鎌倉へ修学旅行に行きます
Okay, tomorrow our school excursion
to Kamakura finally begins.
"8:30 assemble at school"
"9:30 depart"
Okay, tomorrow our school excursion
to Kamakura finally begins.
All of the do's and don'ts are
written in your guidebook,
細かい注意事項はしおりに書いてあるので
so be sure to read through it thoroughly.
しっかり読んでおくように
皆さん　当然わかっていると思いますが
As I'm sure you are all aware,
while this is an excursion,
it is still a part of your studies.
旅行といっても　あくまで授業の一環です
"Trip Guide"
"Mukawa High School"
ルールやマナーを守って
"Trip Guide"
"Mukawa High School"
Observe all rules and manners,
高校生として　責任ある行動をとるように！
and conduct yourselves like
responsible high-schoolers.
Okay, quiet down!
は～い　静かに～
見て見て！
Look at this.
"Enoshima"
It's National Route 134,
the Shonan Bullet Road!
湘南弾丸道路　国道 134 号線！
"Enoshima"
It's near the inn where we'll be staying.
Want to go see it during our free time?
私たちが泊まる旅館の近くなの　自由時間に見にいってみない？
It's near the inn where we'll be staying.
Want to go see it during our free time?
道を見るだけなんてつまらない
Just looking at a road isn't any fun.
そりゃそうだけどさぁ
Okay, sure, maybe not,
じゃあアンタは他に楽しみでもあるっていうの？
but do you have something else
you're looking forward to doing?
高座豚ハム　三崎の魚料理に　鎌倉スイーツ
Kozabuta ham, the fish dishes of Misaki,
and Kamakura's sweets.
Food?
食べ物？
少ない奨学金から毎月積立金払ってたんだから
I've been saving a reserve fund from my
meager scholarship money every month,
so I need to let myself
splurge a little bit.
それくらいの贅沢はさせてもらわないと
Hmm. Well, maybe I'll go
and see it by myself.
じゃあ一人で見にいこうかしら
You're kidding me.
ウソでしょ…
Yes. I have a fever.
はい… 熱が出てしまって
はい… 欠席ということで
Yes.
I'll have to stay home.
はい… 失礼します…
Goodbye.
Are you kidding me?
ウソでしょ…
"1. Regarding clothing"
"(1) Wear your uniform properly."
"(2) Choose specified, comfortable shoes."
"2. What to prepare for the trip"
ジャージも制服
Gym clothes count as a uniform.
There.
よし
甲州街道から国道 137 号に入るか
I could take the Koshu Highway
to National Route 137.
相模湖まで走って　412 号を南下するか
Then go up to Lake Sagami
and head south on Route 412.
上り坂が多いのは…
If I'm watching out for
lots of uphill climbs...
I guess I can't tell from this.
これじゃあわからないか
うん
いってきます
Off I go.
Good.
よし
危ないから　やめといたほうがいいわよ
It sounds dangerous.
You probably shouldn't.
やっぱり危ないかな？
Is it really that dangerous?
If I tell you to stay put,
would you listen?
やめろって言われたらやめる？
Hmm...
Maybe I'll listen next time.
次からやめるかな
アンタもバイク乗りっぽい思考になってきたわね
You're really starting to think like
a biker, aren't you? All right.
わかったわ　先生には言わないでおくけど
I won't say anything to the teacher,
着いたら　私からも頼んであげる
but I will plead your case
with you when you do arrive.
気をつけてね　疑わしきときは行かない
Be careful, okay? If something
seems questionable, stay away.
何かあったら迷わず止まる　引き返す
If anything happens, don't hesitate
to stop, then turn around.
Mm-hmm. Thanks, Reiko.
うん　ありがとう　礼子
ここまで 1 時間半弱
Just under an hour and
a half to come this far...
このまままっすぐ南下して　箱根の山を越えて小田原で国道 1 号線
If I head straight south from here,
I'll hit National Route 1 at Odawara
once I'm over the Hakone mountains.
そこで左に曲がって神奈川　湘南経由で鎌倉か…
I'll turn left there
and head for Kanagawa.
From there it's Kamakura by way of Shonan.
I'll go left at the
Hagiwarakita intersection
萩原北交差点を左に曲がって　国道 246 号線
and take National Route 246.
It's kind of the long way around,
少し遠回りだけど　山越えはこっちのほうが楽
but it's easier to get over
the mountains this way.
んっ？
"School Excursion Itinerary 2"
17 時か…
17:00, huh?
御殿場？
Gotemba? Wow, you're making good time.
へぇ　順調じゃない
A little too good. I might arrive
at the inn ahead of you.
順調すぎて　先に旅館に着いちゃいそう
Hmm...
けど　早く来たってやることもないだろうし
You know, there's nothing
to do if you get there early.
Why not enjoy your trip a little?
そっちも旅行を楽しんできたら？
"Motorcycle parking"
Oh, mm-hmm. Thanks.
あぁ… うん
ありがとう
Oh, mm-hmm. Thanks.
"Roadside Station Subashiri"
"Fuji Azami Line"
"Mt. Fuji Subashiri Trail"
I'll let you off with just
this much for today.
今日はこれくらいで勘弁してあげる…
国道 134 号線… 湘南弾丸道路
Route 134.
The Shonan Bullet Road.
"Shonan Ohashi Bridge"
"Enoden Kamakurakokomae Station"
I should probably get going.
そろそろかな
Huh?
あれっ？
どうしたの？
What's the matter?
おい　アイツなんでここに？
Hey, what's she doing here?
休みじゃなかったのか？
I thought she was staying home.
I'm glad you made it here.
よくここまで来たわね
うん
Mm-hmm.
まったく… 事故にでも遭ったらどうするつもりだったんだ？
Honestly, what would you have done
if you'd gotten into an accident?
Well, we can't exactly turn her away.
まぁ… 追い返すこともできませんし
It goes without saying that
during the excursion,
当然ですが　修学旅行中はバイクの使用は禁止　いいですね！
you are not allowed to ride your
motorbike. Is that understood?
Yes. I'm so sorry about this.
はい　すみませんでした
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
The important thing
is that nobody got hurt.
無事だったからよかったものの…
Yes, and she does appear to
be sorry for what she did.
まぁ　反省しているみたいですし
I suppose so.
そうですね…
Aww, I'm exhausted.
疲れた
Thanks.
ありがとう
でっ？
Well?
Let's go hit the baths.
お風呂　入りにいこう
行こう！
Let's go!
Well? Well?
で？でっ？
I went up Mt. Fuji.
富士山登ってみた
Mm-hmm, Mt. Fuji. Oh, yeah?
フーン… 富士山…
へぇ
I had to drop down to first gear
before Station 4,
四合目の手前で一速に落として
and then managed to get
to Station 5 that way.
それでなんとか五合目まで辿りつけた
The Cub's first gear is there to
climb any uphill slope in Japan.
カブの一速は　日本中のあらゆる坂を登るためにあるんだから
The story is that when you get up a tough
mountain road on an off-road bike,
オフロードバイクで過酷な山道を踏破したら
there'll be an old man there on his Cub,
picking wild vegetables.
現地の山菜とりのおじいちゃんがカブで来てたっていう話もあるし
尾道や長崎みたいな坂の町で　車じゃ登れない勾配の先にある家まで
On steep roads like the ones
in Onomichi or Nagasaki,
Cubs make deliveries every day to homes
past slopes that cars can't climb.
配達カブは毎日通ってるのよ
Cubs are superior, all right.
やっぱりカブは優秀か
Of course they are. They're the best.
当然じゃない　最強よ
Oh, that's right. I went down Route 134.
あっ　そうだ
134 号線も走ってきた
Huh? The Shonan Bullet Road? No fair!
えっ！湘南弾丸道路！ずるい！
私より先に行くなんて！
How could you go there before me?
Early bird gets the worm.
早い者勝ち
ずるいずるい　裏切り者！ もう
It's still not fair! You traitor! Jeez...
Hey, you asleep?
ねぇ… 寝た？
What is it?
なに？
About our free time tomorrow...
明日の自由行動だけど…
お土産にキャラメッ子買っていこうよ
Let's go buy some souvenir
kurumicco candies.
あっ　リスに会いたいね
I hope we see some squirrels.
That would be nice, huh?
会えるといいね
Here it is.
あった
Why do you have that?
なんで持ってるの？
You can never be too prepared.
備えあればなんとやらよ
やっぱり私たちは山よ！
We really do belong up in the mountains!
"Kanazawa-hakkei Station"
It looks like my Cub has had it.
私のカブ… もう終わりみたい
The engine, the electricals,
and the suspension are all shot.
エンジンも電装も　足回りもだめ
What's more, the frame is cracked.
それに　フレームにヒビが入っちゃっててね
So... what are you going to do?
で… どうするの？
That's why I'm thinking
of buying a new Cub.
それで新しいカブを買おうと思うの
Someone I know has a shop
with some CTs for sale.
知り合いのショップが CT の出物があるって言うから
A CT is a Hunter Cub, right? The kind
of Cub that goes up mountain roads.
CT って　ハンターカブのことでしょ？
あの山道を走るカブ
そうよ
That's right. They stopped
making them in 2012,
2012 年に製造終了して
and the remaining distributor's
inventory is all gone.
しばらく残っていた流通在庫ももう終わり
They're still in demand even now overseas.
今でも海外じゃ需要あるのよ
They call them Farm Bikes,
ファームバイクっていって
and they're the service vehicles
they use on farms with huge fields.
バカでっかい畑や牧場で働く人の実用バイク
新しいモデルが出ている
There are newer models out.
Do you think those
electronically controlled Cubs
あんな電子制御のカブに　CT の後継が務まると思う？
are any kind of successors to the CT line?
The era of the Cub being the world's
greatest Farm Bike is over.
終わるのよ…
カブが世界最高性能のファームバイクだった時代が
I just need to take good care of my Cub.
自分のカブを大切にすればいい
Heh, well, of course. I mean, it's a Cub.
そりゃそうね　だってカブだもん
I'm sure that even ten years from now,
you'll have no trouble finding parts.
きっとあと 10 年たっても部品に困らない
ずっと走り続けるわ
You'll be able to ride it forever.
Do you think so?
そうかな？
When you buy your Hunter Cub,
let me ride it, too.
ハンターカブ　買ったら私にも乗らせて
慣らしが終わってからね
Once I get it broken in. I'm going
to ride the heck out of it until then.
まずは私がじっくり乗るんだから
礼子の言うとおり　50 年後　100 年後の世界でも
I wonder if, like Reiko says,
50 years from now,
or 100 years from now,
Cubs will still be consistently running.
カブは変わることなく走り続けているだろう
私も変わらない　変わりたくない
I'm not going to change.
I don't want to change.
いつまでも走り続けよう　このスーパーカブと一緒に
I'm going to keep riding forever.
Together with my Super Cub.
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ
"Super Cub Episode 7"
"The Girl of Summer-Sky Aqua"
Episode 7: "The Girl of Summer-Sky Aqua."
第 7 話　「夏空の色、水色の少女」